hey folks welcome back to the second
half of the Dark Horse podcast
livestream number seven we are going to
answer your super chat questions I am
sitting with dr. Heather huiying I am
going to do a better job
I promise of speaking into the
microphone it's harder than it looks
mm-hmm all right all right that further
ado we are going to embark on these
questions question number one
looking at the toilet paper hoarding
from an evolutionary standpoint do you
believe gender differences could be
playing a role and would men or women be
the more likely culprit playing a role
good one roll of toilet paper
oh it's spelled differently you spellers
are all alike yeah what do you think you
want to address that yeah I think women
are more likely to be hoarding toilet
paper right I'm not sure I love the term
hoarding I don't know if we've talked
about this on the live stream but the
idea of planning ahead and having a back
supply of things that you need is not
inherently hoarding if you never did it
before and you're panicking maybe that
looks like hoarding but if you always
tend to have a lot of something around
I'm not sure that that should be
qualified as hoarding but put that aside
women in general are more likely to be
putting stuff away and saving and
planning for for later situations I
think and also women use toilet paper
more for you know women you store the
paper every time they use the bathroom I
think
whereas men only used two other paper
when they're actually sitting there on
the toilet so I think it's safe to say
women are probably more likely to be
stockpiling toilet paper and men are
more likely to be left scratching their
heads wondering why it doesn't drop from
the sky like normal perhaps yes I would
say I find the whole toilet paper
phenomenon curious because as much as I
get that people are stocking up even on
stuff that's not absolutely essential I
think this is more a reflection
action of human and securities than it
is a response to the particular crisis
in question you know this could get kind
of biological in nature but I gotta say
if the toilet paper I mean some people
wise people aren't using toilet paper to
begin with they've moved on to some
version of a bidet that's healthier for
the body and you know if the if the hot
water continues to run toilet paper
isn't your only go to move so a whole
lot of the world doesn't use toilet
paper and this I mean we we cannot
continue to spend so much time on the
first question in front of time at the
end but back when I Madagascar
you know I embarked on these five months
field seasons and would have to plan out
what am I gonna need for five months and
one of the things was how much does a
person and her field assistant and which
toilet paper does one person and they
feel assistant or for the field season
you were with me on two people and the
field assistant used in five months
because at that point anyway there was
literally no possibility of buying
toilet paper anywhere in Madagascar it's
just not what they used and you know
it's such a desperately poor country
that it was not going to be a luxury
item that started to be used it's not
that people don't clean their butts they
do so they just don't do it with paper
do it some other way yes
in Madagascar even the concept of toilet
was a bit foreign in most locations all
right let's move on alright so this we
have several questions from echo which
thank you I know know how to pronounce
your name assume that virus X has become
innocuous and a rat species can it cause
radical diet change for instance if all
pandas who fed on virus Laden rats died
and only those able to eat bamboo to
survive yeah so first of all when you
say innocuous we presume that you mean
that it has become a some harmless to
the creature that is not consistent with
it radically changing diet because
presumably the animal that would be
infected has a diet choice that is honed
based on whatever the opportunity cost
of the various
foodstuffs that are available are so if
the virus alters what the animal is
feeding on it's moving away from
whatever selection had chosen as the
right diet for that habitat so those two
things are a little bit inconsistent but
your point about could a virus alter the
the food preferences of an animal yes
this is readily possible and I would
just say that if we look at
toxoplasmosis in rodents which is a
parasite that alters the behavior of
rodents such that they are more likely
to be ingested by cats cats being the
place where the the pathogen reproduces
we see exactly this kind of alteration
and it's not the only case there are
many places where pathogens alter
behavior to increase the likelihood of
their being passed on not all of them
match that model you proposed but enough
things are close that yeah it's readily
possible and follow-up here could
awareness for the possibility of
catching a potential virus be one of the
reasons why some animals don't like the
company of other species could that be
one more reason than food to defend
territory the question about defending
territory is particularly interesting I
think I think yes potentially yeah I
would say it's certainly true that to
the extent that viruses or any other
pathogen leaping between species carries
a cost that it will be it will schedule
how reluctant creatures are to interact
and I will also say that I've seen as a
mammalogist I've seen ectoparasites
attempt to abandon a sinking mammal you
know where an animal dies and it's got
fleas and those fleas are now in a
desperate race to find some other
animals so from the point of view of
anything that would mess with that
carcass like a scavenger there is going
to be a cost-benefit analysis is the
meat worth the ectoparasites or you know
if it's a raptor maybe the ectoparasites
aren't very well adapted to jump to the
raptor so it
be a better food item for a bird than
another mammal for example I will say I
think actually that the default
assumption here may be flipped that
organisms are not Basel II that is
primitively but we tend not to tend to
try not to use that word in evolution of
biology we talk about the basal state
the earliest state organisms tend to be
solitary and develop involve sociality
rather than our social and evolved away
from sociality not that that doesn't
happen but that if the default
assumption is one of being relatively
solitary we tend to end up trying to
explain why sociality evolves rather
than excuse me rather than why
solitariness evolves that said we know
for instance that in cases of let's see
migrating shorebirds who end up in these
mass nesting colonies in Alaska and the
Pacific coast of Canada that their nests
become it's not virus but another
pathogen they have these ectoparasites
that become that their nests become
filled with such that they have a
limited time that they are going to be
in those nests so they are they are
social but in a temporary temporarily
restricted way so there's mass
aggregations and then once there once
their broods are reared and they're
migrating again they tend to
disaggregate yes all right our another
question from so there's four questions
here from echo our animals aware of more
things than we assumed yes
depends who you are and what you say yes
but they but they know but they are
aware of things that probably some
animals are capable of inferring
information about the world that we have
very little concept of so I will say
I'll pull in both directions on this one
animals are frequently aware of things
that you don't expect them to be aware
of on the other hand awareness and
conscious are two different things and
some at some point we will talk about
consciousness but I would just say that
there is
next to no reason to hypothesize
consciousness in a great many organisms
that behave in a beautifully interactive
way in other words consciousness that is
subjective experience is costly and not
necessarily beneficial with respect to
accomplishing many of the beautiful
things that animals do so don't leap to
the assumption that just because an
animal behaves in a way that a conscious
animal might that it is inherently
conscious in many cases it will almost
certainly turn out not to be the case
what's so interesting I read aware I
immediately sonata my's that with
sensory inputs you know what kinds of
sensory inputs to do other animals have
that we either don't have in as is
higher form you know our sense of smell
is much reduced compared to the other
mammals or that we don't appear to have
at all things like electro sensory
perception yep and I would just say the
way to think about this is if you look
up at the canopy of a forest you will
see that the trees actually have
interlaced with each other that they
don't spend a lot of time overlapping
and they really don't spend a lot of
time crashing into each other right
they've sort of navigated the space in
some way that suggests the kind of
awareness and we know it has nothing to
do with a conscious awareness subjective
experience etc it's a kind of passive
awareness but elegant good and final
question from echo Brett would people
who look younger than their age have
longer telomeres any studies on
different ethnicities telomere lengths
yeah I would be a little bit cautious
about people who look younger that is
that is too broad but yes you will find
any tissue that has a below average
level of damage at a given age will
leave that individual younger in that
tissue that can be your liver it can be
your skin we know a lot about how this
works in skin with collagen matrix but
basically rule of thumb would be that if
a tissue looks younger and I would
the gold standard would be under a
microscope if the tissue looks really
well-organized like it came from a young
animal it probably is chronologically
younger by virtue of having gone through
fewer cell divisions to get where it is
and you know we also empirically I would
just say there's a lot of truth to the
fact that you know 60 is the new 40
right there's a way in which our lives
just do so much less damage than our
immediate ancestors you know because you
know we do certain kinds of damage
sitting at a desk or whatever but by and
large our lives are physically a lot
easier than they were even a century ago
and so hard lives we're down you're
replicative capacity rapidly and to the
extent that you're spared that you do
retain youth longer which is desirable
this part of why I'm so troubled by the
campaign to end human aging is that
actually if we got over that we know a
ton about how to how to keep you healthy
longer and the returns on research
investments that go towards how do we
slow the aging process not by magic but
by you know making life better and
healthier those returns are great and we
are ignoring them gambling on something
that I think will never come to pass
which is actually correcting the aging
problem in the living organism without
disrupting its ability to function good
I don't know anything about this next
question Brett so I'm going to read it
although I know that I don't have the
one guy's name pronounced correctly
London real had the video removed banned
from LinkedIn and more after the
interview with David Icke hickey on 5g
rights and freedom issues wackos are not
targeted what do you guys see there
since broadly a question about 5g but I
don't know the particular references
he's making yeah and I'm not I'm not too
far ahead of you I'm sort of aware that
there is a story but I couldn't even
tell you what it is so maybe this is
something somehow we need a better
mechanism for remembering what we've
said we're going to look into I know I
dropped the ball on a couple you can
highlight that that line in the in the
super chat google thing great
all right good viruses have evolved
could good viruses have evolved sub
mechanism to self-regulate their rate of
replication to maximize transmission and
the time the host keeps transmitting
isn't it probable in viruses like kovat
19 like SARS cough - yeah yeah I would
say absolutely you would expect viruses
to naturally evolve to regulate their
rate for maximum levels of transmission
sometimes that will be produced as many
as possible right so inside of a cell
that's been infected that might even be
the rule but how much how much
transmission to a new host is
accomplished by invading new tissue
within an already infected host is an
interesting question
and the more transmission between cells
the more compromised the host is going
to be so as we've talked about before in
the case of many but not all pathogens
they benefit from not making you so sick
that you can't move around and spread
them so they will evolve in the
direction of regulating their
pathogenicity within the host to leave
you on your feet and the more
specialized the transmission maximizing
between hosts of the same species the
less likely probably that the virus will
be able to jump species right so the
more the more specialized your virus is
the less likely we're going to see it if
it started out in the bat or a Pangolin
or a Sibbett or camel or whatever
whereas these more generalized
transmission vectors are the ones that
we're going to see and part of probably
why we see something that looks kind of
just regulated on the part of the virus
right now you know i think i think i
think most people have dropped the
expectation now that this will clearly
follow the seasonal pattern and we'll
see less of it in the north american
summer because there doesn't seem to be
any evidence of that from the south
america from the southern hemisphere
summer and from more tropical climes but
really this is about as we've talked
about earlier this is about
this particular virus being a completely
new to the human host it's not that the
virus is new to life on this planet but
it's very new to its relationship with
us yeah it it has no experience with us
and so even if it's well regulated for
its original bat host it's not clear
that it even has the signals to follow
the same pattern right you know in a
human so I would say in the case of
covert 19
we're in some sense waiting for it to
figure out what its interests are we I
do expect some decrease in the
transmissibility from a number of
different sources one is what we talked
about last time UV light being an
effective killer of the thing so to the
extent that it's brighter and they're
more hours of daylight that suggests a
positivity that has nothing to do with
the cyclic pattern of the pathogen
itself and also if it is true that we
are seeing and again there's a couple of
studies that say that we're seeing
something like half a percent to one
percent of the total infected population
are showing up on reports of Ovid 19
cases if that holds from the Scottish
data and elsewhere then what it suggests
is potentially a sizable fraction of the
population growing immune over time
without being symptomatic and that also
predicts something has nothing to do
with seasonality but as we head towards
the northern summer we're also heading
towards greater herd immunity right
which is what we want yep that's that's
the best outcome can you recommend some
books for any of that from any of the
vast branches of biology I left the
question somewhat vague to give more
room for interpretation we will have
recommended reading associated with the
book that we are writing but I guess I
can do three right off the top of my
head
Selfish Gene by Richard Dawkins is from
1976 is still the classic it's a little
dated but and you know could use could
use an update but it's excellent mother
nature by Sarah black for her tea is an
extraordinary
investigation of the evolution of not
just parenting and mothering but sex and
gender more broadly and baboon
metaphysics by Cheney and Seyfarth a
married couple who worked on in case of
this book baboons in the Okavango Delta
of Botswana and they looked into to what
degree baboons have things like theory
of mind and are able to interpret to
realize not just that other beings exist
but that they have different
understandings about the universe than
they do yep maybe I'll add a couple
others to Guns Germs and Steel that's an
awfully good one from the point of view
of understanding how biology and
humanity interface and just for fun
there's a great book that you and I have
taught from called tropical nature oh
yeah which if you want to get a handle
on how things are different in the
tropics it's a great place to start so a
really good book and if when this
lockdown is lifted and people are able
to travel again it is the book that we
recommend for people going to the
tropics and actually you know explain to
explore tropical nature you want this
book in your hands especially if it's
the Neotropics yeah that's fact I would
go so far as to say it is essential
reading so Amazon should send it to you
even if you're in Michigan yes because
you heard it here first from tropical
biologist there you go there it is and
we would know we would know did the use
of ancient psychotropic plants by early
hominids cause a genetic disposition to
addiction or are social constructs a
greater actor in this hmm I see no
reason to imagine a genetic disposition
but but I'm not gonna blame psychotropic
plants or early hominids for one thing I
don't think either one of them would
listen to us but I will say we are
coming to understand over time that the
model of addiction is more complex than
many people have thought and not built
of the stuff that we usually assume so
well Heather and I have come to
understand from years of thinking about
these things is that
boredom is a much greater contributor to
addiction than anything else even these
predispositions that people genetically
have basically function when you don't
have a better choice so and there are
some there's a rat study I think that
bears this out right but I think it's
rats that you you offer them and I don't
remember it's it's coke or meth or one
of these one of these powdered drugs you
offer it to them in a cage bereft of
anything to do and of course they become
addicted and you enrich their lives with
things that enrich the lives of rats I
don't know if that's wheels to run in or
television to watch I have no idea I
don't remember but they'll try it
they'll try the the lever and and and
take some but but they don't become
addicted at nearly as high rates yeah so
a rat study bears it out probably a bear
study would rat it out absolutely you
wouldn't want to have this stuff to me
yeah a lot of really not math no any
thoughts on the three-toed skink
regarding its Amba parity here's the CNN
article so we were able to look at one
and only one of these questions in
advance and we both saw that because
skinks right why would you tell them we
looked it up it's so much cooler to just
pretend that we happen to know this
particular study I did so neither of us
did and I still I only looked at the CNN
article so I have not we did not have
time to look at the paper that it was
based on but it seems that there is a
skink that was both a vaporous and the
vaporous meaning that a individual both
laid eggs and gave live birth and that
is not supposed to happen right that in
general species well it gave it I think
I think what the study said was that it
laid eggs and it gave life birth sort of
within the confines of what would
normally be expected in a single
pregnancy but there are snake species
that do this there's snake species that
depending on where they are in their
range they will sometimes be of a
vaporous that is giving live birth and
sometimes be a vaporous I don't think
it's within a single individual although
it's harder these are these are these
very nasty and aggressive African snakes
that I'm thinking of I can't remember
the species there a couple of them um
but it you know begs the question it's
it's amazing if individuals can do both
but why in general the question is you
know why why lay eggs versus why give
birth egg-laying is the basal state to
return to that terminology that vivid
parody evolves later than egg-laying and
there are reversals you can go back to
over parody from vivid parody and
there's also this intermediate state
called ova viv a parody where you have
eggs inside of you that hatch and then I
was gonna ask if that was the mechanism
here yeah so it may well be and at least
the CNN article didn't didn't say but
but just think about you know under what
circumstances you would you would want
if you know if you're having kids if
you're you know pursuing the thing that
evolution has told you to pursue under
what circumstances is it better to have
a clutch of eggs that's totally
defenseless but which you can leave
behind and travel to get food without
the burden of being weighed down by the
eggs or you want all of your brood on
you at all times but whenever you go out
you're fully your kids and you are
suffering the greater weight you're
probably more susceptible to predation
all of that so and then there are also
differences around whether or not the
sex of your offspring is determined by
by chromosomes or by environmental
measures and you basically if you're
going to be of a vaporous you're going
to need to have chromosomal sex
determinations there's all of these
interesting factors here I'm gonna go
the other way and say that this is
actually a totally expected thing what's
not expected is that you will see it mmm
that basically the fact of species that
do both things depending upon where in
their range there are they are and the
fact that over time this characteristic
changes predicts that individuals will
find themselves somewhere in between
some fraction of the time and then we
just almost never see it but wouldn't
your prediction be that it's almost
certainly ovav of a parity then since
vivir parity requires so many distinct
anatomical and physiological adaptations
well right that I mean there are like
four different phenotypes of placentas
within
mammals but all of them have not just a
remarkable number of circulatory
respiratory neurological distinctions
that then also have genetic distinctions
whereas over fever parity okay I've got
eggs do I lay the eggs or do I let the
thing hatch out inside of me and then
give birth like that that seems like a
pretty that's an easy that's an easy one
to get past but the real question I
would say is if you looked across the
phylogeny of snakes if this pattern is
distributed such that we know it has
evolved many times it could be a
facultative thing where the structures
are already latent in the genome yeah
actually breaths I have just the paper
for you it's cool for people like us you
can map the OVA Paraty onto onto the
snake for luncheon nice we just lost
okay if an effective treatment or
vaccine is not discovered before leaving
quarantine have our actions delayed
rather than prevented covered 19 deaths
no I mean both oh yeah both but rather
than no our actions will have delayed
some deaths but they also prevented some
because there will be greater herd
immunity there will the virus presumably
this is a guess but based on other
viruses we will be evolving towards
lesser variance over time and the health
care professionals are learning better
ways to treat so you know you say
effective treatment or vaccine I think
you know we have been skeptical of the
the plan that like it's only about it's
a vaccine or nothing but there are so
many different avenues by which we
trying to approach this that I would say
even so even if we have no vaccine and
just treatments that seem to work in
places and not in others that the
quarantine will have yes delayed some
deaths but also have prevented others I
would add to this there is this lurking
parameter that I think we don't know how
to think about yet
which is low levels of exposure causing
non symptomatic cases that then generate
immunity and we don't know how many of
these we are generating it is possible
that I have been through this that you
got sick with Kovan 19 back in February
and that I had an asymptomatic case we
actually a friend is sending us some
tests and we may know more about whether
or not this is what happened to us
serology tests but in any case many
things are possible including that what
we are doing given the density-dependent
evidence that lower lower exposure
levels result in less serious cases and
that there are many non symptomatic
cases slowing this down may actually be
producing the effect of a vaccine
without us having invented a vaccine so
I think there are lots of ways in which
this is actually moving in the right
direction and as much as I think much of
this had been botched at the
governmental level the population has
actually risen to the challenge
surprisingly well and you know even
absent the silver bullet this could work
out yeah pretty well and with an
endogenous biological vaccine created
through behavioral modification rather
than in a lab yeah on the fifth podcast
you discussed the low success rate of
respirators I think we were talking
about with ventilated entities you know
hypothesizing koban 19 is hungry for
oxygen
somehow attacking hemoglobin if that is
the case would blood doping be a
treatment this is actively being thought
about and discussed in medical circles
and I think we need to leave it to them
to to navigate that but I think the the
evidence for hypoxia as a primary driver
here is less secure than it was there's
been more people have looked into it and
it doesn't look that way on the other
hand the evidence that ventilators that
physical mechanical ventilation
is not highly effective that basically
it becomes necessary as people face
these cytokine storms at the end of very
serious cases oh I should come back to
cytokine storm maybe a little bit later
but as people face these dire
consequences at the end of one of these
very bad cases of kovat 19 the
ventilators become necessary but lots of
people don't live to get off the
ventilator yeah so I think that's where
we are blood doping is a possibility
we've talked about whether or not it
carries immunity factors if it's taken
from people who have had an exposure and
recovered from it or whether or not it
just simply carries increased capacity
to have oxygen in the blood either way
it could be viable but yes there's a lot
to be understood there well kovat 19
proved to be as cataclysmic for academia
as it is for other domains exposing
academia's major structural weaknesses
and inability to adapt we can hope yes I
my answer was not in response to you
know the question yes I think especially
the liberal arts colleges are suffering
greatly and maybe some of the chickens
have come home to roost yeah there are a
lot of chickens in academia I've
encountered quite a number myself I
would I would say that oh we could we
could do a whole live stream about the
chickens in academia but the weaknesses
in academia are being revealed that is a
hopeful thing if it allows what has been
trapped inside of academia to either
upgrade the institution so that the
vital things that academia has
traditionally been in charge of get done
better or that those things find a new
home either way we cannot have science
trapped inside of an institution that
can't figure out for example that men
and women are actually two different
things right you just can't have an
institution in charge of the one
if it's confused about the other for
example this is Pamela Olsen again who
ends her question by asking us to hold
hands and smile again so we're gonna do
that all right
she gives a link which we can't access
right here but says that it says 91% of
deaths are over 55 years old 28.5% are
over 85 the whose site says only 1% of
deaths do not have a comorbid disease
shouldn't quarantine be targeted I think
there's a really good argument for this
and I think with with widespread
serology testing it becomes an excellent
argument that once we know especially
including who has already been exposed
the big if they're being that we are
assuming that if you've been exposed and
have recovered that you cannot be
infected again at least right away that
then doing targeted quarantine would
seem to be a very good intermediate
stage that would not be putting so many
people at risk of economic disaster I
would add to this so the the reason it's
not a simple question is because even if
the people who are dying are older and
therefore you could potentially free
younger people to go about their
business those younger people may be
circulating things that then reach those
older people and so this is why I raised
the question before about about
effectively I think the the academic
term is Sanel aside if you know we are
effectively taking old people and
leaving them to the wolves that's
presumably not something we want to do
and so keeping those people safe may
involve a general quarantine but the
other thing I unfortunately did not have
time to fully digest it but I read the
beginnings of a very interesting article
written by
one of the founders of Instagram Kevin
whose last name escapes me other people
will know it but anyway he was arguing
for a metric which was I believe R sub T
which would allow you to compare
different methods of quarantine for
their effectiveness at reducing the
spread of the disease and thereby in
essence we could figure out how is it
that we could liberate people who are
less endangered by this and not put
those who are in danger at greater risk
etc so better metrics and as you've been
saying since moment one much higher
rates of testing those are absolutely
necessary yeah and some of the changes
we've seen with regard to the quarantine
could persist you know I think it's
pretty widespread at this point at least
in the US and I suspect at least some
places elsewhere as well that grocery
stores for instance are now starting out
their day by having an hour for only
elderly and other maybe
immunocompromised people and sure it's
less convenient for those of us who
prefer to shop first thing in the
morning but it makes a lot of sense and
those those sorts of things could
continue on for a very long time while
perhaps freeing us freeing the rest of
us in some greater ways next question
universities are announcing austerity
cuts that impact key instructors what
models would allow those fleeing these
colleges to claim emergent online
learning terrain outside a university
system if you build it they will come
yeah so I think that's right that's not
a model but sorry go on well I mean what
we need is for the gatekeeping to be
ended by this situation or something
else so that those who can deliver the
goods without the huge overhead of the
massive administrations and other
absurdities that go along with modern
colleges and universities that those
people are liberated to deliver the
educational goods and to discover how to
do
outside of that system I guess I would
also say that although I know what's
going on at a few schools I don't know
more widely and my assumption is that
because it's so much easier to cut
non-tenured faculty adjunct and
non-tenured faculty and even people on
tenured track but without without tenure
yet that those are the people who are
being cut first and those are the people
of course who were exactly doing almost
all the teaching so one effect that we
may see here is that you have higher ed
becoming more and more a bastion for
research and and you know what has been
clear to undergraduates at big
universities for a very long time is
that for the most part the big the big
name academics either never never show
up in classrooms or if they do they
certainly don't have time to actually
think about teaching or to engage with
undergraduates so this this separation
of education from research of
scholarship from education is is a
problem and I think this will put that
an even starker relief but to the degree
that the people who are being let go
from there
higher ed jobs were primarily in
educational roles rather than research
roles they may be better positioned to
figure out how to teach online than if
someone with 40 years of NIH grants but
no experience in the classroom were
suddenly unable to get grants and yet
lost is hard money position at an art
one but we have a situation in which a
visionary needs to figure out how to
take the people who are gifted with
respect to teaching to compile them get
them paid give them a a path forward in
the in a career that that makes sense
and can feed a family and that can
actually deliver something to students
that is not only enriching to them but
also is recognized by the outside world
as valid you know part of this comes
down to the fact that you've got a
stranglehold on education that comes
from the fact that only these
institutions are licensed to give you a
credential that's worth anything
and so lots of people are going to these
institutions not because they believe in
them but because that's where the
credential comes from that then is the
gateway to a job and so somebody has to
figure out how to break the stranglehold
and you know this is one of the place
places where those who are in love with
the idea of economic competition are
just absolutely right which is if if the
universities had to compete head-to-head
with something on the outside that
delivered higher quality educational
goods that were equally valid in the
marketplace for careers the universities
would get better it is the fact that
they have an effective monopoly through
accreditation and other mechanisms that
has made them so feeble a bit off topic
but if you haven't seen Richard
Linklater's movie waking life or how
they recommend it okay is there a
hashtag we can use to tweet you possible
topics for your podcast haven't we
should do that okay but we aren't going
to figure that out right now yeah okay
you can try a dark-horse podcast try
that or darkhorse suggestions I don't
think we should do this yeah let's not
do it live edit you want to note that
Zachary thank you
and then this is another question okay
it's blocked I can't see it about this
david icke ER ikke interview making
outlandish claims this one about SARS
Cove to being our hoax with evidence so
I think two of our questions have come
at that from different angles and we
don't know enough about it to assess
next one octopodes octopi or octopuses I
think that we should actually defer to
Toby our younger son on this who was a
master of creating plural names for
animals such as he's for horse and I
can't actually member anymore at the
beaks fake self obviously yeah so I
believe I got schooled in my own class
that I insisted that octopi was correct
and octopuses is also correct oh they're
both
yeah that's what I that's what I came to
understand years ago fair enough
could the left/right political spectrum
have evolutionary origins dating as far
back as the early mammals 65 million
years ago I'm wondering if the curiosity
fear axis could have evolved as a
left-right axis we see today so I'm
gonna let you take that but I'm gonna
first just correct mammals actually
didn't originate with the KT boundary
when when the meteor hit at Chicxulub
good modern Yucatan and in fact there
are good
phylogenetic models that suggest that
there have been mammals around for 200
million years but you know it's not
clear if all of the current clades
including you know primates and cats and
rodents and bats were around 65 million
years ago or if they were still just a
bunch of basal scurrying mammals running
around and that caused the the vast
adaptive radiation but we didn't
originate that way we are from much
longer ago than that but do you want to
take the political question yeah I think
I mean the political spectrum is a
feature of a moment in time but there is
something and we actually address this a
bit in the book that we are currently
writing and revising there is a basic
dichotomy between let's say stasis and
progress with progress being risky but
the mechanism that opens up what we call
frontiers so yes this will be a very
ancient process but I don't even think
it's early mammals we've made the
argument that this is actually an
evolutionary feature that will cover all
tax they even ones that don't have a
cognitive capacity bacteria yeah there
there is a a tension between modes and
so anyway we'll talk more about that at
some other point but yes there is
something to the idea that those kinds
of divisions that we find in our
cognitive political space actually have
roots that go far back into our distant
ancestor or past
which excuse me what should the
productive conversations of geometric
unity theory look like and what platform
so they live on talking to the wrong
brother yeah you got the wrong Weinstein
yeah I don't I don't know how to answer
that question I think the fact that we
are talking about geometric unity in
public is very healthy and I look
forward to seeing where it goes but Erik
that's a question for you clearly that's
right your thoughts on a virtual
Convention on freedom and rights in
light of the crisis now your thoughts on
a virtual Convention on freedom rights
in light of the crisis and would you be
interested in participating in such a
conversation yeah I don't know that you
even need the current crisis and I will
say that I think most of the people who
were involved in conversations about how
we might remake civilization
productively were motivated by a fear of
just how fragile our current
civilization has become and so 5-10
years ago right now yeah so for some of
us you know I don't know anybody who saw
the particulars of this crisis emerging
as they did but wow there were a lot of
us who were awfully nervous that people
seem to have gotten complacent about the
hazards we face and the hazards were
looming ever-larger Salutations super
people thank you
there's been chatter on the
philanthropic front philanthropic front
lately about the possibility of kovat
related vaccinations and surveillance
campaigns gate seems enthusiastic but
I'm a little worried thoughts what could
possibly go wrong what could possibly go
everyone could possibly go wrong yes
said you know South Korea's track and
trace requires which has been by nearly
everyone's measures one of the most
successful nations statewide measures to
keep this inner Thunder control required
targeted surveillance so I guess I at
the risk of destroying what we've built
up here
yeah I would say look this is this is
the wrong time to be having this
discussion and I understand that we have
to have it because we're in this
situation but a lot of us have been
shouting about the hazard of a
government that appears to be
functioning towards objectives that are
not public spirited and the necessity of
remaking it such that it is accountable
right that is not a new topic for many
of us and so yes we are now in the
situation where we both have to do some
sort of track and trace thing and the
one entity that's really in a position
to do it couldn't possibly be trusted
and even if you say well it could be
done privately you're gonna do it
through your phone is it going to be
Google I don't trust any of these
entities to engage in this kind of
behavior so we're now damned if we do
and damned if we don't
what we should do is recognize never
again we don't want to be in the
situation we need the ability to deploy
some sort of track and trace in order to
deal with the next epidemic without it
inviting this kind of authoritarian
overreach nonsense we've seen so much of
so let's let's fix this and if we can't
fix it for this round let's fix it for
the next one
good a study shows SARS two attacks a
Stu and testes and reduces testosterone
by 50% and recovered patients thoughts
Zak you want to highlight that one
because it's got a link in it I would
say a I haven't seen I feel like someone
pointed this out to us before and didn't
pursue it yeah so just haven't seen the
research a we need to know it's a huge
reduction if that's true what it it's a
huge reduction we need to know what it
means
is does this mean everybody who's had an
asymptomatic case I strongly doubt it
what it's going to mean is people who
had a severe case and is the result
robust I have my doubts about that too
but we could find out that it is is the
result robust but you know nobody's had
this disease for very long so does it
clear up some sort of a year in which
case that's not worry about it if it
doesn't clear up you know over the
course of time
and it raises questions obviously
testosterone is something you could
supplement if you needed to so anyway I
don't see it as the primary concern and
I'd like to know a lot more about it
before saying anything definitive but
you know that number 50 reduces
testosterone by 50% and recovered
patients strikes me as a red flag it
just seems so high yeah but but we'll
take a look ya'll have an email to send
papers of interest to we both have
websites that have emails on them I
think it's support at Brett Weinstein
net yep and hello farmer Burt what mine
is okay that heather hang calm maybe I'm
not sure I'm sure about yours yeah
thoughts on link between positive blood
types and death rate with a sample of
1,500 those with positive blood type oh
we're talking about rhesus factor then
are up to 15 percent more likely to die
from covered 19 interesting we had seen
the a B O blood type paper and talked
about it in one of the early live
streams but I had not seen the rhesus
factor one so I don't have any
particular yeah thoughts here so I would
say this raises some questions for me
which may well be known to other people
but there's some question about why so
in mammals red blood cells do not have a
nucleus the story that we tell about
that is that the nucleus is removed so
that there's more room for hemoglobin to
carry oxygen this raises all sorts of
questions about why the virus is
invading red blood cells to begin with
because absent nucleus is it able to do
anything my guess would be no but I
can't rule it out I should have looked
it up but I can't rule it out without
looking it up because it's possible that
when the nucleus is removed ribosomes
are left behind in which case this
particular virus could continue to
operate in a red blood cell in which
case this would be straightforward if
that was not the case which I assume it
is not the case I don't think there
arrived as ohm's left behind in the red
blood cell but I don't know if there are
no red if there are no ribosomes left
behind in the red blood cells then
there's a question about why these
antigens on the surface of
the red blood cells are playing a
primary role are those antigens also
being some seen somewhere else in the
physiology and so the red blood cells
are a red herring in this case or is
there some meaning you know the the
reason that the corona virus looks the
way it does is that it has these
receptors on its surface which interact
with the proteins on the surface of
cells and so you know getting into a
cell is very frequently and in this case
it is a matter of joining proteins on
the surface of the cell and using them
to I think bind the membrane so it has a
cell like membrane and the lipid
membrane you've heard of in Philips
contents into the the cytoplasm of the
cell so there's a question about whether
that's happening in red blood cells if
so why does the virus want in if it
doesn't have ribosomes with which to
make more virus and I don't know the
answers to those questions but that's
the road I would go down okay yeah so we
are going to stop taking super chair
questions I Q just want to draw a line
on the spreadsheet if you can so that we
know where to stop because we've got a
lot more to get through here and so I
know can't see what the next question is
though let's say if I can find it on
mine
wouldn't you be interested in forming an
alliance of professors in exile ape
academic stakeholders like us will have
more power to influence the Academy as a
group maybe yeah we're always open to
these ideas but we want to see something
that has the potential to do the job
that's really crucial yep hi professors
thank you for these streams Brett last
week you said you were doubting the wet
hmm doubting the wet market origin story
in favor the virology lab can you
discuss your reasons in more depth
before you answer though you're saying
for a biology lab accidental release
rather than I was just gonna say that I
saw an appalling question I think out of
the Pew Research Center then merited by
CNN worse
30% of Americans believe the virus is
architected in a lab and I looked at
this and I just thought you know if I
had been asked this question the answer
that I would give was not available
because I don't believe that this virus
was engineered we don't have evidence
that I believe points in that direction
but there is reason to think that it was
being investigated in a lab and that
that may have been how it was released
so I think you spelled it out there the
question the the question that you saw
was a or B do you think this virus came
out of a lab or not do you think it's
natural or it was engineered in a lab
just not a complete solution set right
so what I you know and I am open to all
kinds of evidence for any other
hypothesis but from what I've seen so
far I would say I think it's a natural
virus I think it was in the lab
potentially for legitimate reasons could
have been illegitimate reasons but that
what happened is a mistake in the lab
caused someone to be infected and you
know that's a natural virus that has
escaped through a lab it's not a or B
and why specifically are you doubting
the wet market Georgian I'm doubting the
wet market origin because I have yet to
see the evidence for a clear pattern
that the wet market was involved and you
know they weren't selling bats the
closest colony of horseshoe bats is a
long ways away you know there was
something else you were we were talking
about Lots so again I don't want it I
don't want responsibility for this story
I don't know I've never been to Wuhan I
don't know anything about their wet
market how it functions under normal
circumstances I don't know whether you
can order bat soup in a restaurant in
Wuhan but what I have seen suggests that
this is not common practice in that part
of the world the bats in question what
is an eating bat soup isn't common
practice isn't common practice there
there isn't from what I understand bats
were not found for sale in the Wuhan
market at the point that this was
suspected the clade of bats which are
understood to be the source of the virus
the quote the closest colony is at least
100 miles away farther it's farther away
than that
that could be wrong maybe there's a cave
I don't know about but the evidence I
saw suggested that and on the other hand
I have seen what credibly appears to be
a job advertisement to study back
coronaviruses at a lab that just happens
to be in Wuhan and so you know where am
i I'm not committed to any hypothesis
yet but I would say the one hypothesis
continues to look weaker the more I see
and the other hypothesis looks stronger
what doesn't look strong to me at all is
the idea that this is an engineered
virus totally engineered it all
engineered yeah or nor do we see do I
think of either of us seen any
compelling evidence that this was
intentional release as a weapon it
doesn't make sense to me that you would
release it close to the virality lab
because it raises too many questions so
yeah you know everything I know so far
suggests accidental release that's not
to say that there weren't lab safety
issues right perhaps you know more so in
that lab than there should have been
that they could have foreseen problems
and all but this this is always a risk
when you are doing this kind of research
in any lab which are which exists
probably in every major city on the
planet that way so I'm still very anti
wet market I mean we effectively know
that HIV came from human contact with a
hunted chimpanzees is that not enough of
a cost for us to end the hunting of wild
animals for the sale and what markets I
think it's sufficient in and of itself
right how much of a role do you think
climate change has to play in increasing
the likelihood of more zoonotic diseases
jumping from wild animals to humans I
hate to say it but I think probably in
the end it reduces the likelihood
because it reduces diversity I think
it's just going to reduce the number of
creatures we're interacting with so I
think in the end it obviously climate
change will reduce diversity but it may
put species in contact with one another
sooner than they would have or you know
at all than they would have in the
shorter term such that you end up with a
shorter term spike in
zoo notic jumping between host species
with a longer term declined because
there's just not as many species to jump
from yeah and it will also create
desperate people who will eat bush meat
who wouldn't otherwise be driven to it
but I would say you know as somebody who
has handled wild mammals regularly in
graduate school you know I studied bats
i netted them I took data and glued
transmitters to him and let him go I
don't know good scientific reason you
handled mouse lemurs yeah I had a good
scientific reason it's just a little
hard to defend but in any case basic
precautions in general have prevented
this kind of transmission as far as we
know there's always the risk that
something is going to jump I think we
need to think about how to deal with
people who do what I did in graduate
school studying these animals you know
how do we make sure that you know not
releasing something into into the human
population is a high on their list of
concerns but by and large if something
had a really easy time jumping to humans
it's already happened and to the extent
that things don't jump so easily to
humans then the point is we need to
prevent intimate contact of the sort
that butchering and cutting your finger
or whatever it is that would cause that
sets in motion so anyway I don't think
it's a straightforward anthropogenic
climate change increases or decreases
I think it's going to be a bit of both
hello again do you think erythropoietin
EPO would help with hypoxia and treating
Koba 19 with the malaria drugs such as
Hydra hydroxychloroquine thanks for all
the insightful ideas to digest while in
isolation I don't know enough enough
about EPO to address this I can't say
all I can say is what I said on the
beginning of the livestream which is
that I've seen two papers this week that
cast doubt on the idea of
hydroxychloroquine being a useful
treatment at least for people who are
already very sick
that I believe was true in both both
papers mm-hmm
amazing work folks keep it up thank you
do you think the fact where are we there
we go not moving it for a second the
problem do you think the fact that China
has controlled this virus of relative
ease points the possibility that this
was a bioweapon intentionally released
the Chinese government has certainly
sacrificed more citizens before thanks I
don't think that we can believe that the
China has controlled this virus with
relative ease I don't think there's any
reason to assume that the data coming
out of China are real or accurate that
said it's true that the Chinese
government has demonstrated willingness
to sacrifice citizens in ways that would
be anathema to people of other nation
states but I just I don't think that
there's any reason to trust the numbers
coming out of China at this point agreed
thank you for the intellectual
informative and engaging broadcast
you're welcome
what's your et Cie your every day carry
your wallet keys etc well even though
we're in lockdown I still put on pants
every day reasons I can't quite
articulate thing yeah I every day carry
I mean well mine's actually less like
when I I mean if you're staying at home
you don't put on wallet and keys and
such but when I do have to go out I now
we're stripped down to a driver's
license and a card and a insurance card
and a single key and my phone so that I
don't have to be playing with a lot of
objects I know know what I was supposed
to answer to this question okay can we
start again
what's your ET cie every day carry your
wallet keys etc when I go out among the
things that I do is I take my phone out
of the case that I have it in at home if
I drop my phone the case protects it
from breaking if I go out I take it out
of the case so that I can wash it when I
get home or sanitize it while I'm out if
I think it's been compromised because I
do find myself interacting with it but
it's an obvious source of contagion if
you know I touched an object at a store
I touched my phone I want to be able to
clean it and so this puts the phone at
risk but I think it's worth it yeah and
we've got sanitizer in the car and in
the truck so that we have we have a way
to clean stuff when we get back into the
vehicle yes and modern phones can be
washed under a faucet yeah but I mean
with regard to the credit cards keys
it's like yeah totally we now know an
economic shutdown and curfews are not
proportional to the actual danger of
this virus whose head should roll first
wow I don't think we know any such thing
and the problem is to the extent that
we've been effective at addressing this
with lockdowns we don't know what the
world would have looked like otherwise
but if you missed our discussion of what
happened in Guayaquil Ecuador I suggest
you look into it because this can get
pretty frightening pretty quick and you
know even with lockdown we've got mass
graves being dug in potter's field in
New York now that's for unclaimed bodies
but nonetheless we have a body crisis in
New York that's causing extraordinary
measures we saw an absolute catastrophe
unfold in Guayaquil Ecuador I think we
have enough evidence that very serious
things occurred and that we hovered at
the edge of something much worse that I
am not prepared to say we overreacted at
all whenever whenever public health
measures work it's easy for the people
who didn't want them in place to say
they were unnecessary yeah and this is
this is forever a permanent problem of
defending measures that were functional
Chesterton's locked down all right right
could the lack of positive tobacco
research because by no funding after the
MSA stopped big tobacco from funding
research not sure what the MSA is to
what the MSA is
no can't figure it out so I think you
know the idea of Big Tobacco funding
research that's looking into whether or
not tobacco is harmful might have
decreased bad research for sure but I
think in fact there was there was a
clear perverse incentive with having Big
Tobacco funding research that is trying
to discover whether or not tobacco is
harmful or not and when it's NIH or NSF
there are other issues with having these
big governmental organizations basically
being the gatekeepers for what questions
you're allowed to ask but the
researchers in that case at least have
no perverse incentive to find one way or
the other so there shouldn't be you
shouldn't find it being biased in the
other direction just because the people
with a clear bias are no longer allowed
to fund research anything else no
libertarianism isn't insane t-brow says
it's a different form of societal
optimization outside of its proper
context any optimization appears insane
it's not a societal optimization it's
essentially the abdication of the
attempt to reach a societal optimization
or it is a misunderstanding of the game
theory that would allow you to imagine
that society full of people who are
individually freed to do as they wish
will optimize for the whole which it
won't
now that said I take a very hard line
with libertarians because I think they
have something dead wrong but I have
also come to understand they have
something dead right and it would be
very valuable if we could tease those
two apart so we could recover the part
of libertarianism that makes sense which
is to say Liberty is a special virtue
and one can reasonably seek to maximize
it if one understands its true nature
rather than understanding you will
maximize realized liberty by maximizing
formal Liberty maximizing formal Liberty
results in
needless failures and so let's please
level up and tease these two things
apart so that we can stop making the
same errors over and over again very
good research question is copan 19 a
planned implemented and managed global
pandemic by orgs using PR tactics to
gain compliance regarding immunization
and every person digital tagging a World
Health order I think that one yeah go
for it um I don't believe we have any
evidence to suggest that it is however
the instinct of those authoritarian
entities to take advantage of a crisis
to advance their ball is essentially
certain we're already seeing it at a
legislative level and we have to be very
concerned and I have to say this is one
of many reasons that I'm very unhappy
with the Democratic Party's choice to
rally around Joe Biden because as I
understand it Joe Biden was actually the
author of a prototype bill for the
Patriot Act which emerged in the crisis
of 9/11 so anyway yes we have a problem
but that doesn't mean that the crisis
was orchestrated in order to advance
these things much more likely that this
is just opportunistic overreach there it
is
opportunistic overreach Masai tribal
wisdom states although washing your
hands and cow urine won't kill viruses
it will encourage you to not there are
solitary soft flies bees and wasps
so are they're solitary ants and if not
why not there are well yeah yes and no
there there there are ants like the ball
ant that forged solitarily but they go
back to homes with lots of big scary
homes lots of scary pollen in fact
permit me oh you don't have bullet ants
in the studio okay lucite ice cube in a
lucite ice cube that I made back when I
was a graduate student experimenting
with lucite
so anyway this is an ant you can't
really see it it has wings
it's a reproductive ant and it is of a
species that we have encountered yep
this is para poner so this is a giant
verifying forages solitarily but they do
live in colonies so it's not truly
solitary I think the answer to your
question is I don't I think maybe there
aren't any then that are entirely
solitary yeah is that right I think that
is I think that's right but we're gonna
find out because yeah somebody will
correct us yeah and if not why not like
what what makes it's different I'm
trying to remember with regard to the
phylogeny of the Hymenoptera are ants
basil
I mean bees and wasps certainly our
sister but I I just I don't remember I
don't remember how it falls out and
where the saw flies are because I think
they're hymenopteran but they're like
maybe they're the most basal I don't
know I don't know how it falls out yeah
I don't either
I seem to recall wasps were basil but
maybe that's wrong that feels I don't
know jack we need to help that's right
we we know an apt guy yeah he's probably
not watching thanks to the three of you
these are so great could you do my job
for me this is the steel band podcast
could you do my job for me and steel man
social media our ability to coordinate
solutions disseminate critical info
expose foe expertise it's not without
faults but didn't you just do it social
media well I mean look it's the same
it's the same thing over and over again
it's not the Box it's the business model
that's what I used to say about
television and lo and behold things like
HBO proved that that's not to say HBO is
flawless but it's to say that when you
liberate television from a model where
it has to keep you in your seat between
commercial breaks it produces a much
higher quality good social media
absolutely sucks why because of the
nature of the corporations that deploy
it in the market and their obligations
in general to their shareholders but
to their owners in any case that can't
possibly go well same thing goes for
your cell phone these things are all
potentially fantastic technologies that
are hamstrung by the way they are
plugged into the market and
unfortunately because they belong to
these Goliath like corporate entities we
can't replace them with something that
would do the job that's positive without
being predatory and that's really the
predicament we're stuck in what we need
is the phone and the social media
platform that actually has our interests
at heart
and we just can't get there from here
have really enjoyed these streams thanks
I'm curious about the skull and the desk
oh yeah
the skull on the desk is a yeah now
you've done it
okay that is a seal skull that I
acquired from a seal who was no longer
using it he was no longer using it
especially as I disassociated it from
him and that made it impossible to use
it but he had actually died of
presumably natural causes and washed up
on a beach in Oregon where I violated
the law by removing his head with a
knife that was way too short for the job
I did this in the head light of a pickup
truck driven by a student friend of mine
who had found the animal and it caused
quite a kerfuffle on the field trip that
I was on where many people had a moral
objection to my having recovered the
head of this animal for the purpose of
generating this beautiful skull even at
least some people had a legal objection
understanding that you would in fact
broken the law yeah I mean I guess but I
the discussion was an interesting one
because lots of people found what I did
distasteful even though they had a hard
time putting their finger on exactly
what the problem was now it turns out
that what I had engaged in was actually
kind of dangerous behavior because there
are a lot of things you can get from a
sea mammal like this one and diseases
yeah oh yeah bad ones so anyway I got
lucky I got this fancy
skull here it has served me well I've
demonstrated to many classes how these
the skull of a seal looks just like the
skull of a bear except for the teeth and
there's a reason for that which is that
as far as we understand it seals are
actually bears and if that sounds like a
preposterous statement then allow me to
defend it to you at some point because
it's literally true somewhere around
here we have a bear skull from Alaska
next time yeah
please explain your objection to the
lesser of two evils calculation how is
Biden not preferable to Trump Wow yeah
we're gonna have to go deeper into this
later but let me just say this my
objection to the lesser evil paradigm is
twofold one it doesn't hold up if you
think about elections as an iterated
phenomenon in other words it requires us
to think about elections individually
and then say well okay they may both
suck but this one sucks less obviously
you're gonna vote for them right on the
other hand if the point is actually no
my objective is that humans are still on
this planet five hundred years from now
and I think both of these guys leave the
basic problem intact and therefore I'm
looking for whatever solution gets us
through that bottleneck it's a very
different question
so that's that's that's the primary
objection
the secondary objection is that things
like the Democratic National Committee
have used the lesser evil paradigm in
order to keep us trapped and not cater
to the interests of the public so having
abandoned the interests of working
people decades ago the way they keep us
from fleeing the party in favor of some
alternative has to do with the fact that
all they have to do is deliver something
that at the particular cocktail parties
we go to is treated as a lesser evil and
we will be hamstrung and we will just
simply roll our eyes and vote for their
person one more time and at some point
when somebody uses that mechanism to
control you you have to not do what
they're expecting so lots more to say
but
another time which organisms follow us
and a conscious a scale I'm not sure
what follow us oh you mean hell they
want who is next most conscious this is
a easy way I think it's dogs that is
domestic dogs and not incidentally it is
a result of their coevolution with us so
that's I realize a paradoxical maybe we
should leave it leave that answer there
for further expression number another
time but also say those organisms that
are long-lived social with generational
overlap and have long childhoods tend to
be more conscious than not so you can
fill in the gaps it's the other great
apes it's many monkeys it's dolphins
elephant and elephants and willows and
parrots and crows and many others but
all toothed whales not just dolphins but
Yap those other critters are high on the
list you is the dogma of original sin an
example of your factually false
metaphorically true and could utopianism
be a pitfall that it is attempting to
avoid trying to parse that one obviously
original sin would be a literally false
metaphorically true idea how it
functions I don't know we could make
several arguments could utopianism be a
bit I think utopianism is just a it's an
overall it's a response to an overly
reductive understanding of improvement
and the fact is utopians
create disasters because they see one
thing that they want to fix and they
focus on it without understanding
trade-offs it's as simple as that
so it assumes a static world yep
thoughts whether male homosexual
preference is caused by a pathogen
that's too common to be mutational
pressure identical twins are usually
discordant 75% of the time it's hell on
Fitness not found in hunter-gatherers
nope it's an adaptation yep just grab it
there leave it there I recognise you
you're probably
screaming at your screen now champion
adaptation because how would it be
passed on we'll get there
is it crazy to be fearful of the idea of
forced vaccination my girlfriend
suggests it's crazy but I think it's
reasonable to be fearful of the idea of
forced vaccination this is this is hard
it's not crazy to be fearful yeah
is there a circumstance in which it
would be necessary to force vaccination
and you would have to overcome your
fears I think there are rational places
where that could well emerge but figure
out where that line is is really really
hard yes and I think we've done a
terrible job our safety system is so
broken that we you know to force people
to vaccinate would be reasonable if the
vaccines were so safe that for the
benefit to the herd of producing the
immunity it was necessary to require it
but that puts the burden on the system
to make the things very very very safe
and the problem is the economic model
doesn't support it so anyway as I have
said elsewhere we have vaccinated our
children we are strong believers in the
importance of vaccines but we are well
I'll speak for me I am livid that we
have been as cavalier about drug safety
and medical procedure safety as we have
been and if you want me to become an
enthusiastic advocate for things like
mandatory vaccination then you gotta
make these things safe good can you talk
about viral examp demand COBIT 19 I had
chickenpox as a child but I recently was
diagnosed with it again mid-march after
traveling to Western Asia where I like
had to be covered or chickenpox who I
wouldn't think those two things would
look like the same at all yeah I don't
know chickenpox is fascinating internet'
is a virus that goes latent inside of
people who've been exposed so
there are many possibilities possible
you encountered a strain that was far
enough from the one that you had had
before and so were capable of being
infected also you know possible it was
going who knows yep okay three more
questions
I'm gonna go bottom to top here okay
would you like to discuss decentralized
legislators on your show the null
hypothesis of politics.com decentralize
legislators you know I've encountered
other potential solutions to what that
must be a response to but I
decentralized legislature is not
I can't even quite tell what it would be
I mean in some sense we have a
decentralized legislature by virtue of
the fact that it is sourcing people from
all over the country and compiling them
and so it's given us a a link to learn
more maybe from my research most
vaccines are manufactured using animal
tissues and may therefore introduce
animal based virus to humans if vaccine
science controls and quality are as safe
as possible
why should manufacturers receive
immunity well this is a can of worms to
be sure immunity from being sued yeah
here's the reason I think we have to
steal man it before we attack it the
reason is because if we need vaccines
produced then we cannot leave those that
we are asking to produce them in the
frightening position of being sued over
things they could not reasonably have
foreseen and the very fact that we say
well you're making it with animal tissue
therefore something could jump that's on
you
you might drive everybody out of the
race to produce these things so there's
an argument for it but what I would say
is it isn't clear to me at all and I
rather suspect otherwise that the
production of these things for profit is
a bad idea
and so there's a question about whether
or not you want to generate a public
effort to create the vaccines that would
not have the same fears or incentives
and then could render them as safe as
possible which is really I think the
ideal solution which is where all the
libertarians who follow us will now be
apoplectic because I've advocated
government doing something that we don't
want government and aptitude
compromising but the point is what we
need is higher quality government and I
do believe that's possible
final question can you talk more about
rent-seeking sure rent-seeking
effectively is the utilization of a
bottleneck to recover profits that are
the result of non-productive behavior in
the market and my contention is that we
tend to imagine based on what we've all
been taught from classical economics
that rent-seeking exists but that it is
a small perturbation on a system that by
and large functions as the textbook says
and the more I think about it and the
more I read the more I discover that
rent-seeking may in fact be an ever
larger fraction of the economy and that
it would become so as a result of the
what we would call the adaptive
landscape of opportunities that the
market provides in other words this is
not the result of evil people you know
it's not that you're born a rent seeker
but everybody is looking for
opportunities to profit in the market
and the question is do they have good
opportunities that don't involve rent
seeking and if they didn't have good
opportunities but they did have rent
seeking opportunities wouldn't you
expect them to discover that and anybody
who opted not to would be leaving the
door open to anybody who would so we
would expect to see the growth of rent
seeking operations anywhere and
everywhere it's possible so in any case
rent seeking is a huge problem
it is a doubly huge problem when you
have governmental corruption built into
your structures as we do because those
who make their profit through
rent-seeking and that will it's not that
these people are inherently round
seekers it may be that you
people who have been very productive and
20% of their fortune is the result of
productivity and 80 percent of their
fortune as the result of rent seeking
and they probably don't even know the
difference so the problem is when rent
seeking produces profits and profits
produces political power through some
sort of corruption very often legal but
immoral then what you get is a system
that becomes built around protecting the
interests of rent seekers and that's
where we find ourselves so let's fix it
ok we have one more question then all
right for Bret are we experiencing some
sort of social collapse in the West it
may be a bias on my part but we seem to
be moving inexorably towards some climax
socially geopolitically and economically
I would say we are experiencing a gentle
apocalypse which are calling it the
rolling a pocket the rolling apocalypse
all right it's a mild apocalypse yes we
are you know if you read our upcoming
book you will find us discussing the
meaning of close calls what this is is
actually an almost ideal close call for
us to understand almost everything
that's wrong with our system so that
when this happens again next time we
can't say this caught us off guard so my
hope here is that this is mild enough
that we get through it without a major
depression without massive quantities of
deaths all of those things but I
certainly hope that it leaves an
indelible mark and that it puts an end
to certain childish nonsensical notions
about how things have never been better
because yeah things have never been
better at one level and they've never
been more dangerous at the very same
time so here we are great place to end
all right yeah well it's been great we
will see you next time which if
everything goes according to plan will
be Friday Friday all right
you will be well stay safe and we'll see
you Friday
you